<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
	<!-- 
	     draft-rfcxml-general-template-annotated-00
	  
	     This template includes examples of most of the features of RFCXML with comments explaining 
	     how to customise them, and examples of how to achieve specific formatting.
	     
	     Documentation is at https://authors.ietf.org/en/templates-and-schemas
	-->
	<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>  <!-- Required for schema validation and schema-aware editing -->
	<!-- <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?> --> 
	<!-- This third-party XSLT can be enabled for direct transformations in XML processors, including most browsers -->
	
	<!DOCTYPE rfc [
	  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
	  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
	  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
	  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
					]>
	
	<!-- Extra statement used by XSLT processors to control the output style. -->
	<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
	<!-- Processing Instructions- PIs (for a complete list and description,
	     see file http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html.
	     You may find that some sphisticated editors are not able to edit PIs when palced here.
	     An alternative position is just inside the rfc elelment as noted below. -->
	<!-- Some of the more generally applicable PIs that most I-Ds might want to use -->
	<!-- Try to enforce the ID-nits conventions and DTD validity -->
	<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
	<!-- Items used when reviewing the document -->
	<!-- Controls display of <cref> elements -->
	<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
	<!-- When no, put comments at end in comments section,
	     otherwise, put inline -->
	<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
	<!-- When yes, insert editing marks: editing marks consist of a 
	     string such as <29> printed in the blank line at the 
	     beginning of each paragraph of text. -->
	<?rfc editing="no" ?>
	<!-- Create Table of Contents (ToC) and set some options for it.  
	     Note the ToC may be omitted for very short documents,but idnits insists on a ToC 
	     if the document has more than 15 pages. -->
	<?rfc toc="yes"?>
	<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
	<!-- If "yes" eliminates blank lines before main section entries. -->
	<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
	<!-- Sets the number of levels of sections/subsections... in ToC.
	   Can be overridden by 'toc="include"/"exclude"' on the section
	   element-->
	<!-- Choose the options for the references. 
	     Some like symbolic tags in the references (and citations) and others prefer 
	     numbers. The RFC Editor always uses symbolic tags.
	     The tags used are the anchor attributes of the references. -->
	<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
	<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
	<!-- If "yes", causes the references to be sorted in order of tags.
				 This doesn't have any effect unless symrefs is "yes"
	          also. --> 
	<!-- These two save paper: Just setting compact to "yes" makes savings by not starting each 
	     main section on a new page but does not omit the blank lines between list items. 
	     If subcompact is also "yes" the blank lines between list items are also omitted. -->
	<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
	<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
	<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
	
	<!-- Information about the document.
	     category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
	     For Internet-Drafts, specify attribute "ipr".
	         original ipr values are: full3978, noModification3978, noDerivatives3978), 
	         2008 IETF Trust versions: trust200811, noModificationTrust200811, noDerivativeTrust200811
	         2009/Current: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902, pre5378Trust200902
	     Also for Internet-Drafts, you must specify a value for attributes "docName" which is 
	        typically the file name under which it is filed but need not be.
	     If relevant, "iprExtract" may be specified to denote the anchor attribute value of a
	        section that can be extracted for separate publication, it is only useful when the value
	        of "ipr" does not give the Trust full rights.
	     "updates" and "obsoletes" attributes can also be specified here, their arguments are
	        comma-separated lists of RFC numbers (just the numbers) -->
	<rfc
	  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	  category="info"
	  docName="draft-livingood-low-latency-deployment-08"
	  ipr="trust200902"
	  obsoletes=""
	  updates=""
	  submissionType="independent"
	  xml:lang="en"
	  version="3">
	
	
	  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->
	
	  <front>
	
	    <title abbrev="ISP Dual Queue Networking Deployment Recommendations">ISP Dual Queue Networking Deployment Recommendations</title>
	    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-livingood-low-latency-deployment-08"/>
	
	    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->
	    <author fullname="Jason Livingood" initials="J" surname="Livingood">
		   <organization>
	           Comcast
	       </organization>
	      <address>
	        <postal>
	          <city>Philadelphia</city> <region>PA</region>
	          <country>USA</country>
	        </postal>
	        <email>jason_livingood@comcast.com</email>
	      </address>
	    </author>
	
	    <date month="April" day="21" year="2025"/>
	
	    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->
	    <!-- WG name at the upper left corner of the doc,
	         IETF fine for individual submissions.  You can also
	         omit this element in which case it defaults to "Network Working Group" -
	         a hangover from the ancient history of the IETF! -->

	    <workgroup>Independent Stream</workgroup>
	
		<!-- You can add <keyword/> elements here.  They will be incorporated into HTML output
	         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff output. -->
		<!-- <keyword>Text</keyword> (as many of those elements as needed -->
	

	    <abstract>
	      <t>The IETF's Transport and Services Working Group (TSVWG) has finalized experimental RFCs for Low Latency, 
	      Low Loss, Scalable Throughput (L4S) and new Non-Queue-Building (NQB) per hop behavior. 
	      These documents describe a new architecture and protocol for deploying low latency networking. 
          Since deployment decisions are left to implementers, this document explores the potential 
	      implications of those decisions and makes recommendations that can help drive adoption and acceptance of 
		  L4S and NQB.</t>
	    </abstract>
	
		
	  </front>
	
	  <middle>
        <!--  <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
	      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
	      document are to be interpreted as described in
		  <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t> -->

	    <section title="Introduction">
			    
		<t>The IETF's Transport and Services Working Group (TSVWG) has finalized RFCs for Low Latency, 
		Low Loss, Scalable Throughput (L4S) and Non-Queue-Building (NQB) per hop behavior <xref target="RFC9330"/> 
		<xref target="RFC9331"/> <xref target="RFC9332"/> <xref target="RFC9435"/>
		<xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-l4sops"/> <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-nqb"/>. These documents do a good 
		job of describing 
		a new architecture and protocol for deploying low latency networking. 
		But as is normal for many such standards, especially new or experimental ones, certain deployment decisions 
		are ultimately left to implementers.</t>
		
		<t>This document explores the potential implications of key deployment decisions and makes 
		recommendations for those decisions that may help drive adoption by network operators and application 
		developers. That is a key issue for low latency networking, because the more applications developers 
		and edge platforms that adopt 
		new packet marking for low latency traffic, then the greater the value to end users, so ensuring 
		it is received well 
		is key to driving strong initial adoption.</t>
		
		<t>It is worth stating though that these decisions are not embedded in or inherent to L4S and NQB per se, 
		but are decisions 
		that can change depending upon differing technical, regulatory, business or other requirements. Even two 
		network operators with the 
		same type of access technology and in the same market area may choose to implement in different ways. 
		Nevertheless, this document 
		suggests that certain specific deployment decisions can help maximize the value of low latency 
		networking to end users, network operators, and application developers.</t> 
		
		<t> In addition, the design of the protocols also make clear 
        that applications developers are best positioned to understand the needs of their applications and to, 
        by extension, express any such low latency needs via appropriate L4S or NQB packet marking.</t>
		
		<t>For additional background on latency and why latency matters to the Internet, please 
        read <xref target="BITAG"/>.</t>
	
	    
	    <section title="A Different Understanding of Application Needs">
		    <t>In the course of working to improve the responsiveness of network protocols, the IETF 
			    concluded with their L4S and NQB work that there were two main types of traffic 
			    and that these two traffic types could benefit from having separate network processing queues 
			    in order to improve the way the performance of delay-sensitive and/or interactive applications. 
				In addition, introducing a new queue better supports incremental development of a new standard 
				rather than changing existing congestion control algorithms - which would be complex.</t>
			    
			    <t>One of the two major traffic types is mostly file download or upload, such as downloading an operating 
				system update or uploading files to a cloud backup. This type of traffic tends not to be particularly 
				delay-sensitive, at least on a millisecond level basis. The other type of traffic is real-time, 
				interactive traffic that is typically latency-sensitive, such as video conferencing and gaming.</t>
			    
				<t>The value of dual queue networking (simply "low latency networking" hereafter) 
				seems potentially good, and at least one major ISP has deployed it <xref target="Comcast"/>. 
				It seems possible that 
					this new capability might enable entirely new classes of applications to become possible, 
					driving a wave of new Internet innovation, while also improving the latency-sensitive 
					applications that people use today.</t>

		</section>
		
		<section title="New Thinking on Low Latency Packet Processing" anchor="NewThinking">			
			<t>L4S does *not* provide low latency in the same way as previous technologies like DiffServ Quality 
			of Service (QoS). That prior 
			QoS approach used packet prioritization, where it was possible to assign a higher 
			relative priority to certain application traffic, such as Voice over IP (VoIP) telephony. This approach 
			could provide consistent and relatively low latency by assigning high priority to a partition 
			of the capacity of a link, and then policing the rate of packets using that partition. This 
			traditional approach to QoS is hierarchical in nature.</t>
			
			<t>That QoS approach is to some extent predicated on the idea that network capacity is 
			very limited and that links are often highly utilized. But on today's Internet, many users have 
			experienced poor application performance, such as video conferencing, despite having sufficient bandwidth. 
			In many of these scenarios, prioritization will not improve a flow. But finding a way to reduce latency 
			has proven beneficial. This new low latency networking approach is not based on hierarchical 
			QoS prioritization. Rather, it is built upon conditional priority scheduling between two queues 
			that operate at best effort QoS priority.</t>
			
		</section>
        </section>

        <!--  END MAJOR SECTION --> 
        <!--  START NEW MAJOR SECTION --> 
	    
	    <section title="Key Low Latency Networking Concepts">

        <t>In the past, many thought that the only way to improve application quality was via more bandwidth or 
		by using QoS priority. The advent of low latency networking enables a re-examination of those approaches.</t>
	    
			<section title="Best Effort Priority">
		    	<t>Low latency traffic to is not prioritized over other 
				(best effort priority) "classic" Internet traffic. That is the case over the ISP network and the 
				broader internet, though it may not not necessarily be the case for a user's in-home Wi-Fi network 
				due to the particulars of how the IEEE 802.11 wireless protocol <xref target="IEEE"/> functions 
				at the current time - see <xref target="RFC8325"/>). In addition, some user access points 
				may prioritize certain traffic (such as gaming) and some traffic such as NQB may use the 
				AC_VI Wi-Fi link layer queue <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-nqb"/>. This best effort approach stands 
				in contrast to prior differential quality of service (QoS) approaches or to what has been discussed 
				for 5G network slicing <xref target="CDT-NN"/> <xref target="van-Schewick-1A"/> 
				<xref target="van-Schewick-1B"/> <xref target="van-Schewick-2"/> <xref target="van-Schewick-3"/>.</t>
	    	</section>
	    
			<section title="Shared Throughput">
		    	<t>Low latency networking flows do not get access to greater throughput than "classic" flows. 
				Thus, a user's total provisioned or permitted throughput on an ISP access network link is 
				shared between both classic and low latency queues.</t>
	    	</section>
	    	
	    	<section title="Access-Agnostic">
		    	<t>Low latency networking can be implemented in a 
					variety of network technologies. For example in access network technologies this could be 
					implemented in DOCSIS <xref target="LLD"/>, 5G <xref target="Ericsson"/>, 
					PON <xref target="CTI"/>, and many other types of networks.</t>
	    	</section>
	    </section>
	    
        <!--  END MAJOR SECTION --> 
        <!--  START NEW MAJOR SECTION --> 

        <section title="Application Developer Recommendations">
        <t>Application developers need to add L4S or NQB packet marking to their application, which will often depend 
        upon the capabilities of a device's operation system (OS) or a software development kit (SDK) 
        <xref target="Apple"/> that the OS developer makes available. In addition, the application server will 
        also need to support the appropriate marking and, when L4S is used, to implement a responsive congestion 
        controller.</t>

        <section title="Delivery Infrastructure for L4S">
        <t>Since L4S uses the Explicit Congestion Notification (ECN) field of the packet header, to ensure 
        ECN works end-to-end, application developers need to be certain that their servers, datacenter routers, 
        and any transit, cloud provider, or content delivery network (CDN) server involved in their application 
        IS NOT altering or bleaching the ECN field. For an application to use the L4S queue, they must mark 
        their packets with the ECT(1) code point to signal L4S-capability or with the Congestion Experienced (CE) 
        code point when appropriate. Coupled with client marking, if an application client or server detects CE marks, 
        it should respond accordingly (e.g., by reducing the send rate), which typically means that the server 
        must be running a "responsive" congestion controller (i.e., is able to adjust rate based the presence or 
        absence of CE marks for L4S traffic - such as DCTCP, TCP Prague, SCReAM, and BBRv2). See Section 4.3 
        of <xref target="RFC9330"/> and Section 4.3 of <xref target="RFC9331"/> for more information about this.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Delivery Infrastructure for NQB">
        <t>Since NQB uses the DSCP-45 code point in the DiffServ part of the packet header, to ensure 
        NQB works end-to-end, application developers need to be certain that their servers, datacenter routers, 
        and any transit, cloud provider, or content delivery network (CDN) server involved in their application 
        IS NOT altering or bleaching a DSCP-45 mark. The server DOES NOT need to run 
        a special responsive congestion controller. However, it is 
        common for networks to bleach or modify DSCP marks on ingress today, so networks will need to change that 
        policy for NQB to work end-to-end (in contrast, ECN is rarely bleached).</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Only Mark Delay-Sensitive Traffic for L4S or NQB">
        <t>It may seem tempting to mark all traffic for L4S or NQB handling, but it may not help in all cases. 
		For example, a video gaming service may benefit from using L4S or 
        NQB for real-time controller inputs and gameplay, while major game software updates would best be left in 
        the classic queue.</t>    
        </section>

    
        </section>

        <!--  END MAJOR SECTION --> 
        <!--  START NEW MAJOR SECTION --> 

	    <section title="ISP Recommendations">
		    
		    <t>Like any network or system, good deployment design decisions matter. In the context of deploying 
			low latency networking in an ISP network, 
		    these recommendations should help ensure that a deployment is resilient, well-accepted, and creates 
			the environment for generating strong network effects.</t>
        
        
        <section title="Allow ECN Across Network Boundaries">
        <t>Traffic sent TO a peer network marked with ECT(1) or CE in the ECN header MUST pass to that peer 
        without altering or removing the ECT(1) or CE marking (see exception below). Traffic FROM peers marked 
        with ECT(1) or CE in the ECN header MUST be allowed to enter the network without altering or removing 
        the ECT(1) or CE marking (see exception below). The only exception would be when a network element is 
        CE-aware and able to add a CE mark to signal that it is experiencing congestion at that hop.</t>
        
        <t>This part - allowing unmodified ECN across the network - is likely to be easier than DSCP-45 for 
		NQB (see next section), since it 
        appears rare that networks modify the ECN header of packet flows.</t>
        </section>
        

        <section title="Allow DSCP-45 Across Network Boundaries">
        <t>Traffic sent TO a peer network marked with DSCP value 45 MUST pass to that peer without 
		altering or removing the DSCP 45 marking (see exception below).
Traffic FROM peers marked with DSCP value 45 MUST be allowed to enter the network without altering or 
removing the DSCP 45 marking (see exception below).</t>

		<t>However, some networks may use DSCP 45 for internal purposes other than NQB within 
		their network. In these cases, the peer using DSCP 45 for other purposes is responsible for 
		remarking as appropriate. If possible, for operational simplicity, a network should 
		try to maintain the use of DSCP 45 on an end-to-end basis without remarking in their interior network hops.</t>
		
        </section>

		<section title="Last Mile Network (Access Network)">
        
        <t>There are two hops of interest in the last mile access network. One will be a point of user aggregation, such as a Cable 
        Modem Termination System (CMTS) or Optical Line Terminal (OLT). The second is at the user location, such as a Cable Modem (CM) 
        or Optical Network Unit (ONU), both of which are example of CPE.</t>
        
       <t>In theses two queues, ISPs should consider using the optional Queue Protection function 
	   <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-nqb"/> <xref target="I-D.briscoe-docsis-q-protection"/>. This can 
	   potentially detect mismarking and take corrective action as needed.</t>

        </section>
        
        <section title="Customer Premise Equipment (Customer Edge)">

        <t>In most residential Internet services, there are typically two equipment modes. One is very simple CPE that hands off from 
        the ISP's access network (i.e., DSL, 5G, DOCSIS, PON) and provides the customer with an Ethernet interface and IP address(es). 
        The customer then connects their own router and wireless access point (often integrated into the router, typically referred 
        to as a "wireless gateway" or "wireless router"). The other model is more typical, which is that the CPE integrates a link 
        layer termination function (i.e., Cable Modem, 5G radio, or Optical Network Unit) as well as a wireless gateway.</t>

        <t>Not all ISP networks support both of these models; sometimes only a wireless gateway is available. Even in this case, some 
        users "double NAT" and install their own router and wireless access point(s) to get whatever functionality and control over their 
        home network that they desire. The cases explored below are commonplace but may not apply to all networks.</t>
           
		<t>In some cases, dual queue networking and associated packet marking is supported up to the ISP's demarcation point - 
                such as in a cable modem. It is recommended that packet markings should pass from such a demarcation point to 
                any attached customer-administered CPE, such as a router or wireless access point. That enables a 
				customer-administered router to implement dual queue networking, rather that it only being possible with 
				ISP-administered CPE.</t>

        </section>
        
        <section title="Inside the Home - Customer Local Area Network (LAN)">

        <t>As noted above with the mention of an integrated wireless gateway, the CPE and router/wireless network 
        gear is integrated into a single CPE device. Even though these are functionally in one piece of hardware, we can 
        think of the wide area network interface and local area network as functionally separate for purposes of this analysis.</t>

        <section title="802.11 WiFi Queuing">
				<t>As noted above with respect to prioritization of packets in the ISP network, all packets should be 
				handled with the same best effort priority in the ISP access network and on the internet. However, in a user's home 
				Wi-Fi (wireless) local area network (WLAN), this is more complicated, 
                because there is not a precise mapping between IETF packet marking and IEEE 802.11 marking,
				 explored in 
				<xref target="RFC8325"/>. In short, today's 802.11 specifications enable a Wi-Fi network to have multiple queues, 
				using different "User Priority" and "Access 
				Category" values. At the current time, these queues are AC_BK (Background), AC_BE (Best Effort), 
				AC_VI (Video), and AC_VO (Voice).</t>

				<t>As explored in <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-nqb"/>, packets in the low latency queue 
				may be expected to be marked for the best effort (AC_BE) or video (AC_VI) wireless queue. For additional context, 
				please refer to Section 8.1 of  <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-nqb"/>. In some situations, such as a 
				user-owned wireless access point or CPE, it may not be possible for the user to select which wireless 
				queue is used. In cases where the CPE is ISP-administered, selecting a specific wireless queue may be 
				possible - though it is not yet clear what the best practice may be for this selection until ISPs and 
				application developers have more experience with low latency networking. As of the writing of this document, 
                it appears that the AC_VI queue may be used for the low latency queue in some networks - and that many 
                latency-sensitive applications are already marking their upstream wireless traffic for AC_VI and AC_VO.</t>
			</section>	

			<section title="Use Permissive Upstream NQB Queue Admission">
				<t>Since the IETF's NQB specification is only recently completed, many applications that have 
				been using other DSCP marks for their latency-sensitive flows have not yet shifted to adopt DSCP-45. 
				One example is the Microsoft Xbox platform <xref target="Microsoft"/>, which is using DSCP-46. 
				So in the relatively short-term, ISPs may find it beneficial to their customers to 
				use a more permissive upstream NQB admission policy, allowing DSCP-40, 45, 46, and 56 admission 
				into the low latency queue. It may take a year or more after the NQB DSCP assignment is made by IANA for  
				developers to shift to DSCP-45, given other items in their development backlog and their 
				software release schedule.</t>

			</section>	
			</section>


        <section title="Do Not Use Middleboxes">
        <t>As noted in <xref target="Tussle"/> there has always been a tension in the end-to-end model between how 
        much intelligence and processing takes place along the end-to-end path inside of a network and how much 
        takes place at the end of the network in servers and/or end user client devices and software. In this new 
        approach to low latency networking, entry into a low latency queue depends upon marks in the packet header 
        of a particular application flow. In practice, this marking is best left to the application edge of the network, 
        rather than it being a function of a so-called middlebox in the ISP network. As explored below, this is 
		the most efficient, least prone to mis-classification, and is most acceptable from the standpoint of 
		network neutrality.</t>
		    
		    <t>The best approach is for applications to mark traffic to indicate their preference for the low latency queue, 
			not the network making such a decision on its own. This is for several reasons:</t>
		    <ul>
		    <li>According to the end-to-end principle, this function is best delegated to the edge of 
		    the network as an architectural best practice (the edge being the application in this case).</li>
		    <li>Application marking maintains the loose coupling between the application and network layers, 
		    eliminating the need for close coordination between networks and application developers.</li>
		    <li>Application developers know best whether their application is compatible with low 
			    latency networking and which aspects of their traffic flows will or will not benefit.</li>
			<li>Only the application (not the network) knows whether a scalable congestion control algorithm congestion control is being 
			used on the application server. Thus, only the developer and server administrator know if they are correctly responding to 
			Congestion Experienced (CE) markings for L4S (see Section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC9331"/>). </li>
		    <li>Application traffic is almost entirely encrypted, which makes it very difficult for networks 
		    to accurately determine application protocols and to further infer which flows will benefit from low latency 
		    and which flows may be harmed because they need to build a queue. It is likely that false positives <xref target="Lotus"/> and false negatives 
			will occur if network-based 
			inference is used; all of which can be avoided simply by relying solely on application marking.</li>
		    <li>The pace of innovation and iteration is necessarily faster-moving in the application edge at layer 7, 
		    rather than in the network at layer 3 (and below) - where there is greater standards stability and a lower rate of 
		    major changes. As a result, the application layer is best suited to rapid experimentation and iteration. Network 
		    operators and equipment vendors trying to infer application needs will in comparison always be in a reactive 
		    mode, one step behind changes made in applications.</li>
			<li>This avoids issues arising from mis-classification of application flows <xref target="Lotus"/>.</li>
			<li>Any application provider should be able to mark their traffic for the low latency queue, 
			with no restrictions other than standards compliance or other reasonable and openly documented technical 
			guidelines. This maintains the loose cross-layer coupling that is a key tenet of the Internet's 
			architecture by eliminating the need for application providers and networks to coordinate and creates 
			an environment of so-called "permissionless innovation".</li>
		    </ul>
		
            </section>


        </section>

        <!--  END MAJOR SECTION --> 
        <!--  START NEW MAJOR SECTION --> 
	
	 
	    <section title="Acknowledgements">
			<t>Thanks to Bob Briscoe, Gorry Fairhust, Mat Ford, Vidhi Goel, Mirja Kuhlewind, Eliot Lear, 
			Sebastian Moeller, Sebnem Ozer, Jim Rampley, 
			Dan Rice, Greg Skinner, Joe Touch, 
            Greg White, and Yiannis Yiakoumis for their review and feedback on this document.</t>
		</section>
	
	    <section title="IANA Considerations">
		  <t>RFC Editor: Please remove this section before
			 publication.</t>
	      <t>This memo includes no requests to or actions for IANA.</t>
	    </section>
	
	    <section title="Security Considerations">
		  <t>The key security consideration pertains to Queue Protection. As the current time, it is recommended that 
		  implementers utilize Queue Protection, to ensure that any traffic that is incorrectly marked for low latency 
		  can be detected and remarked for the classic queue. The necessity of Queue Protection remains something of 
		  a debate, with some firmly believing it is necessary but others believing that it is not needed. The latter 
		  view is that application developers have a natural incentive to correctly mark their traffic, because to 
		  do otherwise would worsen the quality of experience (QoE) for their users. In that line of thinking, if a 
		  developer mismarks, they and/or their users will notice and they will fix that error. However, it is 
		  also conceivable that malicious software could be operating on a user's device or home network and that 
		  malicious software could try to send some much traffic to the low latency queue that the queue or both 
		  queues become unusable. This is quite similar to other "traditional" denial of servce (DoS) attacks, so it 
		  does not necessarily seems unique to low latency networking. But due to the possibility of this occuring, and 
		  low latency networking being such a new approach, it seems prudent to implement Queue Protection.</t>
	    </section>

		<section title="Network Neutrality Considerations">
		    <t>Network Neutrality (a.k.a. Net Neutrality) can mean a variety 
		    of things within a country, as well as between different countries, based on 
		    different opinions, market structures, business practices, laws, and regulations. Generally speaking, 
		    In the context of the United States' market, it has come to mean that Internet Service Providers (ISPs) 
			should not block, throttle, or deprioritize lawful application traffic, and should not engage in paid 
			prioritization, among other things. Net Neutrality concerns can sometimes affect the deployment 
			of new technologies by ISPs, so they should carefully consider regulatory issues when 
			making deployment decisions.</t>

			<t>As it is envisioned in the design of the IETF's new low latency networking protocols, the addition 
			of a low latency queue at a network link is merely a second 
		    packet queue and does not mean that this queue is hierarchically prioritized or that it has more 
		    capacity. As a result, low latency networking appears to pose NO new Net Neutrality issues.</t>

			<t>One key aspect of low latencty networking is that it operates, from the perspective of an ISP's 
			deployment, is application-agnostic. The ISP creates a second network queue on key network links, but 
			does not decide on their own what applications can use this queue. Rather, they add the queue and 
			packet flows are sent to that queue based on packet marking set by application developers. This 
			approach is far superior to older approaches, which caused significant Net Neutrality risks
			<xref target="Lotus"/>, 
			that used middleboxes to attempt to infer applications based on observing packet flows on ISP 
			network links.</t>

			</section>
	    
	    <section title="Revision History">
		  <t>RFC Editor: Please remove this section before
			 publication.</t>
	      <t>v00: First draft</t>
	      <t>v01: Incorporate comments from 1st version after IETF-115</t>
		  <t>v02: Incorporate feedback from the TSVWG mailing list</t>
		  <t>v03: Final feedback from TSVWG and prep for sending to ISE</t>
		  <t>v04: Refresh expiration before major revision</t>
          <t>v05: Changes from Greg Skinner and Eliot Lear</t>
          <t>v06: More changes from Eliot Lear</t>
          <t>v07: More changes from Eliot Lear</t>
          <t>v08: Misc updates from IETF review</t>

	    </section>
	    
	    <section title="Open Issues">
		  <t>RFC Editor: Please remove this section before
			 publication.</t>
	      <t>- Open issues are being tracked in a GitHub repository for this document 
		      at https://github.com/jlivingood/IETF-L4S-Deployment/issues</t>
	    </section>
	    
	    
	  </middle>
	
	  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->
	
	  <back>
	    <!-- References split to informative and normative -->
	
	   <references title="Informative References">
			<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8325.xml"/>
			<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9330.xml"/>
			<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9331.xml"/>
			<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9332.xml"/>
			<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9435.xml"/>
		   <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-tsvwg-l4sops.xml"/>
		   <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-tsvwg-nqb.xml"/>
		   <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.briscoe-docsis-q-protection.xml"/>
		   
		   <reference anchor="BITAG" target="https://bitag.org/documents/BITAG_latency_explained.pdf">
			   <front>
	            <title>Latency Explained</title>
	            <author>
	              <organization>Broadband Internet Technical Advisory Group</organization>
	            </author>
	            <date year="2022" month="January" day="10"/>
			   </front>
		   </reference>
		   
		   <reference anchor="Lotus" target="https://www.eff.org/wp/packet-forgery-isps-report-comcast-affair">
			   <front>
	            <title>Packet Forgery By ISPs: A Report on the Comcast Affair</title>
	            <author fullname="Peter Eckersley" initials="P" surname="Eckerseley">
	              <organization>Electronic Frontier Foundation</organization>
	            </author>
                <author fullname="Fred von Lohmann" initials="F" surname="von Lohmann">
	              <organization>Electronic Frontier Foundation</organization>
	            </author>
                <author fullname="Seth Schoen" initials="S" surname="Schoen">
	              <organization>Electronic Frontier Foundation</organization>
	            </author>
	            <date year="2007" month="November" day="28"/>
			   </front>
		   </reference>
		   
		   <reference anchor="IETF-114-Slides" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/meeting/114/materials/slides-114-tsvwg-update-on-l4s-work-in-ietf-114-hackathon-00.pdf">
			   <front>
	            <title>First L4S Interop Event @ IETF Hackathon</title>
	            <author fullname="Greg White" initials="G" surname="White">
	              <organization>CableLabs</organization>
	            </author>
	            <date year="2022" month="July" day="25"/>
			   </front>
			   
			</reference>
			
			<reference anchor="LLD" target="https://cablela.bs/low-latency-docsis-technology-overview-february-2019">
				<front>
					<title>Low Latency DOCSIS: Technology Overview</title>
					<author fullname="Greg White" initials="G" surname="White">
						<organization>CableLabs</organization>
						</author>
					<author fullname="Karthik Sundaresan" initials="K" surname="Sundaresan">
						<organization>CableLabs</organization>
						</author>
							<author fullname="Bob Briscoe" initials="B" surname="Briscoe">
					</author>
					<date year="2019" month="February"/>
				</front>
				
				</reference>

				<reference anchor="Ericsson" target="https://www.ericsson.com/49bc82/assets/local/reports-papers/white-papers/26052021-enabling-time-critical-applications-over-5g-with-rate-adaptation-whitepaper.pdf">
							<front>
							<title>Enabling time-critical applications over 5G with rate adaptation</title>
					<author fullname="Per Willars" initials="P" surname="Willars"><organization>Ericsson</organization></author>
					<author fullname="Emma Wittenmark" initials="E" surname="Wittenmark"><organization>Ericsson</organization></author>
					<author fullname="Henrik Ronkainen" initials="H" surname="Ronkainen"><organization>Business Area Networks</organization></author>
					<author fullname="Ingemar Johansson" initials="I" surname="Johansson"><organization>Ericsson</organization></author>
					<author fullname="Johan Strand" initials="J" surname="Strand"><organization>Business Area Networks</organization></author>
					<author fullname="Petr Ledl" initials="D" surname="Ledl"><organization>Deutsche Telekom</organization></author>
					<author fullname="Dominik Schnieders" initials="D" surname="Schnieders"><organization>Deutsche Telekom</organization></author>
	
	
							<date year="2021" month="May"/>
						</front>
							
						</reference>

			<reference anchor="CTI" target="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-G.Sup71-202104-I">
							<front>
							<title>Optical line termination capabilities for supporting cooperative dynamic bandwidth assignment</title>
							<author><organization>International Telecommunications Union - Telecommunication Standardization Sector (ITU-T)</organization></author>
			
			        <date year="2021" month="April"/>
		           </front>
			           <seriesInfo name="Series G: Transmission Systems and Media, Digital Systems and Networks" value="Supplement 71" />
						</reference>

			<reference anchor="IEEE" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9363693">
							<front>
							<title>Part 11: Wireless LAN Medium Access Control (MAC) and Physical Layer (PHY) Specifications</title>
							<author><organization>IEEE Computer Society (IEEE)</organization></author>
			        <date year="2021" month="February" day="26"/>
		           </front>
				   		<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/IEEESTD.2021.9363693"/>
			           <seriesInfo name="IEEE Standard for Information Technology--Telecommunications and Information Exchange between Systems - Local and Metropolitan Area Networks--Specific Requirements" value="802.11-2020" />
						</reference>

			<reference anchor="Microsoft" target="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/gaming/gdk/_content/gc/networking/overviews/qos-packet-tagging">
			   <front>
	            <title>Quality of service (QoS) packet tagging on Xbox consoles</title>
	            <author>
	              <organization>Microsoft</organization>
	            </author>
	            <date year="2022" month="August" day="19"/>
			   </front>
			</reference>

			<reference anchor="Comcast" target="https://corporate.comcast.com/press/releases/comcast-introduces-nations-first-ultra-low-lag-xfinity-internet-experience-with-meta-nvidia-and-valve">
			   <front>
	            <title>Comcast Introduces Nation's 
				First Ultra-Low Lag Xfinity Internet Experience with Meta, NVIDIA, 
				and Valve</title>
	            <author>
	              <organization>Comcast</organization>
	            </author>
	            <date year="2025" month="January" day="29"/>
			   </front>
			</reference>

			<reference anchor="CDT-NN" target="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2308.05829">
			   <front>
	            <title>Slicing the Network: Maintaining Neutrality, Protecting Privacy, and Promoting Competition. 
				A technical and policy overview with recommendations for operators and regulators.</title>
				  <author fullname="Nick Doty" initials="N" surname="Doty"><organization>Center for Democracy and Technology</organization>
				  </author>
				   <author fullname="Mallory Knodel" initials="M" surname="Knodel"><organization>Center for Democracy and Technology</organization>
				  </author>
	            <date year="2023" month="April"/>
			   </front>
			</reference>

			<reference anchor="van-Schewick-1A" target="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/103120890811342/1">
			   <front>
	            <title>FCC Ex Parte In the matter of Safeguarding and Securing the Open Internet, 
				WC Docket No. 23-320</title>
				  <author fullname="Barbara van Schewick" initials="B" surname="van Schewick">
				  <organization>Center for Internet and Society, Stanford Law School</organization>
				  </author>
				  <author fullname="Scott Jordan" initials="S" surname="Jordan">
				  <organization>University of California at Irvine</organization>
				  </author>
				  <author>
				  <organization>Open Technology Institute at New America</organization>
				  </author>
				  <author>
				  <organization>Public Knowledge</organization>
				  </author>
	            <date year="2024" month="March" day="20"/>
			   </front>
			</reference>
			
			<reference anchor="van-Schewick-1B" target="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/10323701322790/2">
			   <front>
	            <title>Net Neutrality &amp; Non-BIAS Data Services</title>
				  <author fullname="Barbara van Schewick" initials="B" surname="van Schewick">
				  <organization>Center for Internet and Society, Stanford Law School</organization>
				  </author>
				  <author fullname="Scott Jordan" initials="S" surname="Jordan">
				  <organization>University of California at Irvine</organization>
				  </author>
				  <author>
				  <organization>Open Technology Institute at New America</organization>
				  </author>
				  <author>
				  <organization>Public Knowledge</organization>
				  </author>
	            <date year="2024" month="March" day="20"/>
			   </front>
			</reference>


			<reference anchor="van-Schewick-2" target="https://law.stanford.edu/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/van-Schewick-2024-5G-Network-Slicing-and-Net-Neutrality-Shetler-Steffen1.pdf">
			   <front>
	            <title>Net Neutrality &amp; 5G Network Slicing</title>
				  <author fullname="Barbara van Schewick" initials="B" surname="van Schewick">
				  <organization>Center for Internet and Society, Stanford Law School</organization>
				  </author>
	            <date year="2024" month="April" day="3"/>
			   </front>
			</reference>
			
			<reference anchor="van-Schewick-3" target="https://law.stanford.edu/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/van-Schewick-2024-5G-Network-Slicing-and-No-Throttling-Rule-20240418.pdf">
			   <front>
	            <title>Network Slicing and Net Neutrality: No Throttling Rule</title>
				  <author fullname="Barbara van Schewick" initials="B" surname="van Schewick">
				  <organization>Center for Internet and Society, Stanford Law School</organization>
				  </author>
	            <date year="2024" month="April" day="18"/>
			   </front>
			</reference>

            <reference anchor="Apple" target="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/network/testing-and-debugging-l4s-in-your-app">
			   <front>
	            <title>Testing and Debugging L4S in Your App</title>
				  <author>
				  <organization>Apple</organization>
				  </author>
			   </front>
			</reference>

			
			<reference anchor="Tussle" target="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/633025.633059">
			   <front>
	            <title>Tussle in Cyberspace: Defining Tomorrow's Internets</title>
				  <author fullname="David D. Clark" initials="D" surname="Clark">
				  <organization>MIT Lab for Computer Science</organization>
				  </author>
				  <author fullname="John Wroclawski" initials="J" surname="Wroclawski">
				  <organization>MIT Lab for Computer Science</organization>
				  </author>
                  <author fullname="Karen R. Sollins" initials="K" surname="Sollins">
				  <organization>MIT Lab for Computer Science</organization>
				  </author>
                  <author fullname="Robert Braden" initials="R" surname="Braden">
				  <organization>USC Information Sciences Institute</organization>
				  </author>
	            <date year="2002" month="August" day="19"/>
			   </front>
			</reference>
			
		   
	   </references>
	
	  </back>
	</rfc>
